Guide to the Kathleen Foster Campbell Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Kathleen Foster Campbell papers
1924-1992
YCAL MSS 252
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.42
(1 box)
The Kathleen Foster Campbell Papers consist of correspondence, writings and printed materials that document the relationship between Kathleen Foster Campbell and friends from the University of Chicago Poetry Club, as well as her writings and writings of others. The papers span the years 1924 to 1992.
Campbell, Kathleen
Campbell, Gladys, 1892-1992
Dillon, George, 1906-1968
Haskins, Vernon C.
Henderson, Alva, 1940-
Lesemman, Wilbur
Levin, David
Lewis, Janet, 1899-1998
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Serendipity Books on the Elizabeth Wakeman Dwight Memorial Fund, 2006.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Kathleen Foster Campbell
Kathleen Foster Campbell, born Kathleen Foster, attended the University of Chicago to study poetry. Campbell was one of the early members of the Poetry Club, a group formed in 1917 by students who wished to address the absence of modern poetry in the University curriculum. Other members included Elizabeth Madox Roberts, Arthur Yvor Winters, Llewellyn Jones, Gladys Campbell, Maurice Lesemann, and Janet Lewis. Harriet Monroe, the founder and editor of Poetry Magazine, visited the group often. In 1918, Campbell taught a poetry course formerly directed by Edith Foster Flint. After graduating from the University, Campbell maintained a relationship with the members of the club and the University. Through the Poetry Club, Campbell became a close friend of Janet Lewis and Elizabeth Madox Roberts and eventually married Donald Campbell, an attorney and the brother of fellow writer and Poetry Club member Gladys Campbell. The couple lived in Chicago until Donald Campbell's retirement, when they moved to Carmel, California.
Janet Lewis (1899-1998)
Janet Lewis (1899-1998) was born in Chicago, Illinois and attended the University of Chicago and was an active member of the University of Chicago Poetry Club alongside Kathleen Foster Campbell. Lewis suffered from tuberculosis for several years, leaving Chicago around 1921 to live at the Sunmount Sanatarium in Santa Fe, New Mexico. She was very ill for two years and did not fully recover until 1930. In 1926, Lewis married American poet and critic Arthur Yvor Winters (commonly known as Yvor Winters), who also suffered from tuberculosis and left the University of Chicago during his freshman year to receive care at Sunmount Sanatarium. Neither Winters nor Lewis returned to Chicago and instead settled near Stanford University, where they both taught. Lewis and Winters edited the literary magazine Gyroscope from 1929 to 1931. Janet Lewis wrote poetry and novels but also collaborated with Alva Henderson, a composer for whom she wrote three libretti and several song texts.
Scope and Contents
The Kathleen Foster Campbell Papers consist of correspondence, writings and printed materials that document the relationship between Kathleen Foster Campbell and friends from the University of Chicago Poetry Club, as well as her writings and writings of others. The papers span the years 1924 to 1992.
Arrangement
The Kathleen Foster Campbell Papers are organized into three series: Correspondence, Writings of Others, and Printed Materials. They are housed in one box.
Dial (Chicago, Ill.); American poetry -- 20th Century; Poets, American -- 20th Century; Poets; Brooks, Gwendolyn, 1917-2000; Campbell, Gladys, 1892-1992; Campbell, Kathleen; Dillon, George, 1906-1968; Haskins, Vernon C.; Henderson, Alva, 1940-; Jones, Llewellyn, 1840-1918; Lesemann, Maurice, 1899-; Lewis, Janet, 1899-1998; Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972; Roberts, Elizabeth Madox, 1881-1941; Slavick, William H.; Winters, Yvor, 1900-1968; University of Chicago; University of Chicago. Poetry Club
- Correspondence, 1924-1992; Series I; 0.21
  Arrangement
  Letters are arranged alphabetically by correspondent with a small amount of general and third-party correspondence filed at the end of the series.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, contains letters to Kathleen Foster Campbell from friends, many of whom were members of the University of Chicago Poetry Club. The bulk of the correspondence is from Janet Lewis. Third-party correspondence is comprised of letters to Gladys Campbell and Janet Lewis.
  A highlight of the series is letters to Campbell from Janet Lewis at Sunmount Sanitorium in Santa Fe, New Mexico during her recovery from tuberculosis. They describe Lewis's courtship with Arthur Yvor Winters and her slow recovery from illness. Included with an undated letter are holograph drafts of Lewis's poems, "To W.S.L.," "Song," "The Tennis Players," and "Napoleon at Elba."
  - The Dial (Moore, Marianne), 1926 Jan 28 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Lesemann, Maurice, 1980 Aug 4 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lewis, Janet
    - Letters from Sunmount Sanitorium, Santa Fe, New Mexico, 1924-1926 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
    - Other letters, 1968-1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 6-16)
  - Slavick, William, 1981 Oct 2 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - General correspondence, 1950, 1981, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Third party correspondence
    - Brooks, Gwendolyn to Gladys Campbell, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Lewis, Janet to Gladys Campbell, 1992 Feb 9 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Richards, Dorothea to Janet Lewis, 1979 Nov 23 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Writings of Others, 1924-1981, undated; Series II; .21 linear feet
  The series is arranged alphabetically by author. Each author's writings are arranged alphabetically by title. A group of three poems by George Dillon, Kathleen Foster Campbell and Gladys Campbell are filed together at the end of the series.
  Series II, Writings of Others, is chiefly comprised of poems by Gladys Campbell and Janet Lewis. It also contains poems by George Dillon and Kathleen Foster Campbell, a bibliography of Lewis's writings and an essay by David Levin on Kathleen Foster Campbell's Then and Now.
  Writings by Janet Lewis include poems set to music by Vernon Haskins and Alva Henderson. The series also includes two of Gladys Campbell's poems that were set to music by Wilbur Lesemann, the brother of Maurice Lesemann, and Vernon Haskins.
  - Campbell, Gladys
    - "All That is Beautiful," song, words by Gladys Campbell, music by Wilbur Lesemann, holograph score, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Inscribed "With love and birthday greetings this song, Gladys."
    - "She Hath Done What She Could," drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - "The Snow," song, words by Gladys Campbell, music by Vernon Haskins, holograph score, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Levin, David. "Proven Knowledge: The Poems of Kathleen Campbell," typescript photocopy, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Lewis, Janet, 1924-1981, undated
    - "December" draft, typescript, signed, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - "For Carl Rippen, Sunmount Sanatorium, 1922," draft, typescript, signed, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - "Geometries," draft, typescript, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - "Gull Island," draft, typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - "Lines to a Child," offprint from The Magazine, 1934 Jan (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - "The Manger," song, words by Janet Lewis, music by Alva Henderson, photocopy, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - "No-Winter Country" and "The Golden Land," drafts, typescript, corrected, circa 1924-1925 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - "The Reader" and "Cottages in the Desert," draft, holograph, annotated, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - "The Wonder of the World (for a chorale by Alva Henderson)," draft, typescript, annotated, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Bibliography of Janet Lewis, typescript photocopy, annotated, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - "Memory of Lake Superior" by George Dillon, "Evening Walk" by Gladys Campbell and "Not Fragments" by Kathleen Foster Campbell," color reproductions of three illustrated poems, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Printed Materials, 1962-1981, undated; Series III; 2 folders
  This series contains newspaper clippings about and by Janet Lewis and Yvor Winters.
  - Lewis, Janet, clippings, 1976, 1981, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - "Yvor Winters" Stanford Today Summer 1962 and "The Last of the Mohicans" Wilmington Opera Society program June 1976 (libretto by Janet Lewis), 1962, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 38)